When you were a kid, a single summer felt like it lasted forever.
One school year was an entire era.
Now you blink, and somehow it is December again.
A whole year, gone in what felt like a couple of weeks.
And here's the strange part.
The year did not actually change.
It is still exactly 365 days, the same as when you were 8.
So why does it keep going faster?
And why does it keep getting worse every single year?
The answer has almost nothing to do with time.
It is about what your brain bothers to remember, and what it quietly throws away.
Everyone feels this, and it is weirdly consistent.
Ask a 10 year old how long until summer break, and it sounds like forever away.
Ask a 40 year old where the year went and they honestly cannot tell you.
It is not your imagination, and it is not just you.
Time really does seem to speed up steadily for your whole life.
The clock never changes, the feeling always does.
Now, there is an old answer to this that sounds perfect.
When you are five, one year is a fifth of your entire life, a huge slice.
When you are 50, that same year is just one fiftieth, a sliver.
So each year feels smaller because it is a smaller piece of everything you have
lived, clean, tidy, and mostly wrong.
Because if that were really it, time would just feel like
it shrinks smoothly year after year.
But that is not how it feels.
It feels like some years vanish and a few somehow stretch out.
The real reason is hiding somewhere you would not think to look, your memory.
Here is what your brain is actually doing.
It does not measure time with a clock.
When you look back and ask how long something took,
your brain quietly counts how many distinct memories it made in that stretch.
A lot of new vivid memories and the time feels long.
Almost no memories and it feels like it barely happened at all.
Looking backward, time is not made of hours, it is made of memories.
And memories are made of new things.
So picture being a kid again, almost everything is a first.
First day of school, first bike without training wheels,
first time you saw the ocean, first friend, first concert,
first heartbreak.
Your brain is recording constantly in high detail because all of it is brand new
and it does not want to miss anything.
That is why one childhood summer feels enormous when you look back.
It was not longer than your summers now.
It was just absolutely packed with markers.
It was fuller.
And then you grow up and life slowly turns into a routine.
The same drive to work, the same week on repeat,
same faces, same lunch, same scroll before bed.
And your brain, which is efficient and a little lazy,
stops bothering to write down what it has already seen a thousand times.
It compresses the repeats into almost nothing.
A whole month of ordinary Tuesdays leaves barely a trace.
So when you look back at the year and ask where it went,
there's almost nothing recorded there to measure.
And your brain just shrugs and says, huh, that went fast.
The time did not speed up.
You simply stopped saving the file.
A few scientists think there may be a second layer to it.
That as the brain gets bigger and its wiring gets longer,
the signals travel a little slower.
So you actually take in fewer fresh mental snapshots per second than a child does.
Fewer frames, faster film.
That part is still up for debate.
But the memory piece, the part about routine, almost everyone agrees on.
So here's the quiet truth sitting under all of it.
Time is not actually accelerating.
Your life is not slipping away faster than it used to.
Your brain is just writing less of it down.
Because so much of it now looks like something it has already seen before.
The years do not feel short because they were empty.
They feel short because they were full of the same thing over and over.
And your brain only keeps what is new.
And that is the good part.
Because it means the speed is not locked in.
You can slow it back down.
Not with a clock.
With newness.
A trip somewhere you have never been.
A skill you are genuinely bad at.
A different way home.
Anything your brain is forced to actually pay attention to,
it records in full and recorded time feels long when you look back on it.
It is why one week in a country you have never seen
can feel bigger in memory than three flat months of normal life.
The people whose years feel rich and slow are not younger than you.
They are just collecting more firsts.
So if it feels like the years are flying past,
the trick was never to find more time.
It is to give your brain more that is new.
Take the long way home.
Learn the thing you are bad at.
Every first you hand yourself is one more piece of your life
you will actually remember living.
Time was never the thing speeding up.
You just have a lot more say in it than you thought.