Somewhere out there.
The odds say there is probably alien life.
Maybe a little.
Maybe oceans of it.
Which raises a question almost nobody actually stops to ask.
Even if they are real, could they ever actually get here?
Could anything?
Stan looks up at the stars half expecting an easy yes.
But the true answer hides one of the most staggering facts
about the universe you will ever sit with.
And once you see it, you will never look at that night sky
the same way again.
Start with the closest possible neighbor.
The nearest star to us other than our own sun
is called Proxima Centauri.
It is about four light years away.
Four.
That sounds almost walkable, cosmically speaking.
But a light year is the distance light travels in a year.
And light is the fastest thing that exists around 186,000
miles every single second.
The light landing in your eye from that star tonight
left it more than four years ago.
So four is hiding something enormous.
Because here's the catch that changes everything.
We cannot travel at the speed of light.
Nothing with mass can.
Pushing any object up to light speed
would take an infinite amount of energy.
The universe simply forbids it.
So the real question becomes how fast can we actually go?
And the answer is humbling.
Our fastest spacecraft.
If you aimed it straight at that nearest star
would not take hundreds of years.
It would take tens of thousands.
Voyager, our most famous probe,
would need roughly 77,000 years to get there.
Let that land with one number.
Voyager has been flying away from Earth
for almost 50 years now.
Faster than any of us will ever move.
And in all that time, it has traveled about one light day
from home, one day at the speed of light.
The nearest star is over 1,500 light days away.
We have been going for half a century
and we are barely off the porch.
So now flip it around and put yourself in the aliens' shoes.
For them to cross that same impossible gulf and reach us,
they would need technology that to us
would look like pure magic.
They would either have to travel at a massive fraction
of light speed, which takes amounts of energy
that are almost beyond imagining,
or they would have to break the rules of space itself.
Physicists actually have one idea for that, the warp drive.
The trick is you do not move through space,
you move space around your ship,
like a surfer riding a wave.
And the math genuinely works.
The only problem is it requires a kind of matter
with negative energy that, as far as we know,
has never been found and may not exist at all.
Even our single best real attempt, tiny probes,
pushed by lasers to a fifth of light speed,
would still take 20 years to reach the nearest star.
And that project quietly stalled.
This is not a new puzzle, by the way.
Back in 1950, a brilliant physicist named Enrico Fermi
was just chatting over lunch about the chances of alien life
and he asked a simple question
that has haunted science ever since.
Where is everybody?
Think about it, the galaxy is unbelievably huge
and unbelievably old billions of years.
If intelligent life is common and crossing space
were doable, then somebody somewhere
in all that time should have shown up.
And yet, silence, they call it the Fermi paradox
and one of the simplest answers to it
is also the most humbling.
Maybe nobody shows up because nobody can.
Here is the quiet, strange truth this points to.
The universe might be absolutely teeming with life
and it could still be true that none of them ever meet,
not because they are not there,
but because every civilization is stranded
on its own little island of a solar system.
Separated by gulfs so vast that even light,
the fastest thing in existence takes years
and centuries and thousands of years to cross.
We might be surrounded by neighbors we can never visit.
And it cuts both ways, which is the part we forget.
We are not reaching them either.
For all our rockets and telescopes and ambition,
we have exactly one probe a single light day out
after 50 years of trying.
The aliens may very well be real.
They just cannot get to us and we cannot get to them.
The silence in the sky might not mean
the universe is empty at all.
It might just mean it is so full
and so impossibly spread out that everyone is alone together.
So the next time you look up and wonder
if anyone is out there, the honest answer is probably.
Somewhere they simply cannot reach you
and you cannot reach them not because the universe is empty
but because it is so unimaginably vast
that even light strains to cross it.
We are not alone, we are just very, very far apart.
And a universe that big, that full
and that far flung is not a sad thought.
It might be the most astonishing thing
about being here at all.